<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- #%L Matos %% Copyright (C) 2004 - 2014 Orange SA %% Licensed under the 
	Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except 
	in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0 
	Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed 
	under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES 
	OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for 
	the specific language governing permissions and limitations under the License. 
	#L% -->

<book version="5.0" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook 
      http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd">

	<title>Matos Manual</title>
	<titleabbrev>Matos</titleabbrev>
	<info>
		<author>
			<personname>
				<firstname>Pierre</firstname>
				<surname>Crégut</surname>
			</personname>
		</author>
	</info>
	<chapter>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<section>
			<title>Matos objectives </title>
			<para>
				Matos is a static analysis tool that can analyze a compiled
				mobile java
				application
				(Android or MIDP) and give back facts on its
				potential executions. To do
				this it
				accumulate information from simple
				syntactic checks and from semantic analysis
				mainly
				based on an
				analysis of data flows in the code (using a points-to
				analyis).
			</para>
			<para>
				Matos then uses simple heuristics to give a grade to
				applications that
				can be used to focus
				deeper analysis on the most
				likely sources of problems. It is also
				designed to be relatively
				fast
				so that large number of applications can be analyzed in a
				reasonable
				amount of time.
			</para>

			<para>
				The engine of the tool takes three inputs:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>an application to analyzed with optionally a descriptor
						of
						this application (a Jad file for a MIDP application)
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>A set of rules describing what to search (known as the
						analysis profile or profile).
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>An emulation of the execution platform (MIDP MSA,
						Android,
						with additional libraries.)
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>
			    It produces a result in the form of an HTML file. This result is usually synthesized as a grade that
				can be used to quantify the risk or the lack of quality of the application. Which score is assigned to
				which rule is defined in the analysis profile. The combination operator for individual scores is the addition.
			</para>
			
			<para>
			    Rules usually control the use of a given method. They try to infer the potential arguments passed 
			    to all the uses of those methods and depending on the obtained approximation they will produce a verdict
                that states if there are some potential misuse of the API or not.
             </para>
             <para>   
                Other kind of custom rules control the contents of some fields, the way descriptor files are built or some very rudimantary
                constraint on the shape of the control graph or the layout of objects in memory (shape).
			</para>
			<para>
				Matos as a tool can either be used directly from the command
				line or as a service on the web through a web browser (matosweb).
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Organization of the manual</title>
			<para>The first three chapters will help you use the tool: how to
				install it, how to launch an analysis and how
				to interpret the
				results.
			</para>
			<para> The remaining chapters will help you understand how the
				analysis profiles are organized so that you can customize
				the
				behaviour of the tool.
			</para>
		</section>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>Installing Matos</title>
		<section>
			<title>Command line version</title>
			<para>The tool is provided in a ZIP archive. Unpack it and refer
				to the scripts in the bin sub folder to launch the application. Under
				windows, use <code>matos.bat</code>.		Under Linux, use <code>matos</code>.
			</para>
			<para>
				The Linux script tries to detect your current version of Java
				and
				tries to locate the location of the tool. You can override
				the	location of the tool with the
				<envar>MATOS_HOME</envar> environment variable.
				On Windows you may need to edit the file to get	the correct value of <envar>%MATOS_HOME%</envar> directly.
			</para>
			<para>
			    Some users may want to customize the value of the <envar>TEMP</envar> variable.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Matosweb</title>
			
				<para>
				    The script is very similar to the the command line tool.
 				</para>
			
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Compiling Matos from source</title>
			<para>
				The tool is made of several independent modules tied by maven.
				The following instructions assumes that:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						you have a working internet connection with necessary proxies
						declared (
						<code>http_proxy</code>
						variables)
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>you have a Java 7 JDK installed.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>you have a configured installation of maven that can access
						standard repositories.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						you have an installed Android SDK as described at
						<filename>http://developer.android.com/sdk/installing/index.html
						</filename>
						with all the development environment you are interested in (used
						to check what APIs are used).
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>
				Note: if you are not developping applications, you just need the SDK
				not the
				Android Studio or Eclipse ADT but you must configure it by
				launching
				<code>${SDk}/tools/android sdk</code>
				In the intereactive tool, install all the SDK platforms for relevant
				versions of Android.
			</para>

			<para>
				First you must fetch all the source in a folder where the
				source will
				reside.
			</para>
			<programlisting>git clone
https://github.com/Orange-OpenSource/d2j.github
git clone https://github.com/Orange-OpenSource/matos-profiles.git
git clone https://github.com/Orange-OpenSource/matos-tool.git
</programlisting>
			<para>
				Next you must compile the library that translates DEX bytecode
				into Soot
				internal representation. Soot is an analysis and compiler
				optimization
				framework developped by McGill University at Montreal
				that is used by Matos
				to perform low level static analysis (mainly
				pointer analysis).
			</para>
			<programlisting>cd d2j
mvn install
</programlisting>
			<para>
			You must now compile the stubs representing the different execution
			environments for the mobile applications. In the current
			version, there are stubs for MIDP (complete MSA support with a few vendor
			specific APIs) and Android (Ice Cream Sandwich).
			</para>
			<programlisting>cd ../matos-profiles</programlisting>
			<para>
			edit
			<code>matos-android-database/pom.xml</code>
			and modify the value of the
			<code>&lt;matos.android.sdk&gt;</code>
			element.
			to the path of your current Android SDK.
			</para>
			<programlisting>mvn install</programlisting>

			<para>
				It is time to compile the tool itself. There are two flavors:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						a command line tool in
						<filename>matos</filename>
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						a web application in
						<filename>matosweb</filename>
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<programlisting>cd ../matos-tool/matos
mvn install
cd ../matos-web
mvn install
</programlisting>
		<para>
			The binary is stored in
			<filename>matos-tool/matos-web/target/matosweb-bin.zip</filename>
				It should be expanded in a suitable location.
		</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Adding plug-ins</title>
			<para>Matos can be customized for specific use. Plugins are just
				archives that contain analysis profiles and if necessary some new
				stub execution environments.
			</para>
		</section>
	</chapter>

	<chapter>
		<title>Running MATOS</title>
		<section>
			<title>Web interface</title>
			<section>
				<title>Launching the web site</title>
				<para>
					Launch
					<code>matosweb/bin/matosweb</code>
					. It will create a local server on port 8443 that you can
					access
					with your browser:
					<code>https://localhost:8443/matosweb</code>
				</para>
				
				<para>
				    You can change the value of the port from the default 8443 with the <code>-httpPort</code> command-line option 
				</para>
				
				<para>Matosweb is just a stand-alone tomcat7. Its configuration environment is created in 
				    <filename>matosweb/extract</filename>. </para>
			</section>

			<section>
				<title>On-line administration of the site</title>
				<para>
					Log-in for the first time with credentials
					<code>admin/admin</code>
					and modify the password (menu at the top
					right of the browser
					window,
					<command>password</command>
					entry).
				</para>
				<para>
					The admin user can do analysis but its main purpose is to generate
					new user profiles. Select the
					<command>manage</command>
					entry in the
					top menu. On the new page, type in a new user name,
					select if this
					user has admin right (no by default) and click on
					the
					<command>Create</command>
					button
					The default password of a user is its name and it should be
					changed
					immediately by the
					user.
				</para>
				<para>
					The admin user can also delete users, use the combo box to find the
					user and press
					<command>Delete</command>
					.
				</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Launching an analysis</title>
				<para>
				   Analysis are organized in campaigns. A campaign is just a set of applications to analyze 
				   usually as a batch. It can be useful to launch a campaign again on a set of applications if
                   the security profiles have been enhanced to catch new issues.
				</para>
				<section>
					<title>Campaign definition</title>
					<para>
					First create a campaign from the top view. The only necessary value is an arbitrary name.
					Just click on the "Create" button to create it. The campaign should appear in the table
					with its creation date.
					</para>
					<para>
					Campaigns can then be destroyed if they are no more useful by selecting it (ticker on the
					column #) and clicking on the "Remove" button.
					</para>
					<para>
					Access the content of the campaign by clicking on its name. Now you must define the
					code of the applications and the profile used. This is done in a single step:
					</para>
					<itemizedlist>
					    <listitem><para>Depending if the application is an Android application or a midlet, use the relevant section</para></listitem>
					    <listitem><para>Select a profile. Depending on the version you use, there may be only one or several profiles available</para></listitem>
					    <listitem><para>Select a code file on your disk. It must be an APK file for Android or a JAR file for MIDP.</para></listitem>
					    <listitem><para>Select a jad file on your disk if you have one for a Midlet. Matos profiles usually have rules checking the consistency of JAD files if provided.</para></listitem>
					    <listitem><para>Add the step to the list by clicking on either "Android Step" or "MIDP Step" buttons.</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
					
					<para>
					To remove an analysis step proceed as in the campaign list:
					</para>
					<itemizedlist>
    				    <listitem><para>Select the steps to remove by ticking the box on the first column.</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>Press "Remove selected" button.</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist> 
				</section>
				<section>
				    <title>Analysis</title>
				    <para>
			        You can analyze a selection of steps or all the steps at once. The status should change from
					"TODO" to "SCHEDULED" then "COMPUTING" and finally "PASSED", "FAILED" or "SKIPPED" 
					when the analysis is completed.
					</para> 
					<variablelist>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>TODO</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>this is the initial status, nothing has been done yet</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>SCHEDULED</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>The analysis has been planned, but there are other analysis to do before in the 
								   work queue.</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>COMPUTING</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>The analyzer is working on this item but no result has been produced yet.</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>PASSED</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>The analysis is complete and the score is low enough to consider the application as safe in a first approach</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>FAILED</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>The analysis is complete but there are some problems with the code (malware, bad design)</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>SKIPPED</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>The analysis failed. Is it a mobile application code ? May be you found a bug in the tool.</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
					</variablelist>
					<para>
					When the analysis is completed, a score is defined and it is possible to view the complete analysis report by clicking on the
					score.
				    </para>
				</section>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Command line tool</title>
			
			<para>
			     matos [&lt;options&gt;] [jarfile | jadfile | apk | checklist] 
          
         
  
  
    
            
  
			    
			</para>
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>-d &lt;def&gt;</code></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>Use the security profile named &lt;def&gt;. By default, the profile specifed in the configuration file is used.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			    			  
				<varlistentry>
					<term><code> -o &lt;file&gt;</code></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>Set &lt;file&gt; as output file (or output directory in campaign mode (eg if <code>-c</code> option is set). </para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>-jar &lt;file&gt;</code></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>Analyse this JAR &lt;file&gt; as a MIDP MIDlet, (ignore the one specified in the JAD).</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>-jad &lt;file&gt; </code></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>      Analyse this JAD &lt;file&gt;.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>-apk &lt;file&gt;</code></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>Analyze this Android APK.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term><code>-all &lt;directory&gt;</code></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>Analyse all JAR, JAD and SWF files which are in &lt;directory&gt;.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>																
			

			<varlistentry>
				<term><code>-c &lt;file&gt;</code></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
					    Run the check-list described in &lt;file&gt; (script mode to launch a whole sequence of analyses).
					    Check-list are XML files. 
					</para>
										
				</listitem>
				
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><code>-m &lt;midlet&gt;</code></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>For a single MIDlet analysis, do not analyse all midlets of the JAR, but the one called &lt;midlet&gt;. Multiple -m flags may be given. </para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><code>-tmp &lt;directory&gt;</code></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>  Use &lt;directory&gt; as a temporary directory. </para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><code>-log &lt;file&gt;</code></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Set &lt;file&gt; as log file. </para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><code>-css &lt;file&gt;</code></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Use the CSS &lt;file&gt; to control the style and the layout of the HTML result. </para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><code>-h</code></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Display a help </para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
			
					<section>
					    <title>The campaign file format</title>
					    <para>
					        Campaigns may disapear in future versions of the tool as they are less relevant in this version of the tool than they were in the
					        stand-alone version. Most of the time, the <code>-all</code> option is a simpler alternative.
					    </para>
					
					<para>
						The root element is <code>campaign</code> and it contains a list of
					    <code>anajava</code> (for MIDP) or <code>anadroid</code> (for Android) elements describing mobile applications. 
					</para>
					<para>
					The attributes of <code>campaign</code> are:
					</para>
					<variablelist>
						<varlistentry>
						    <term><code>profile</code></term>
						    <listitem><para>An analysis profile (required)</para></listitem>
						</varlistentry>
					    <varlistentry>
						    <term><code>name</code></term>
						    <listitem><para>A name for the campaign</para></listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
						    <term><code>author</code></term>
						    <listitem><para>an author (optional)</para></listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
						    <term><code>date</code></term>
						    <listitem><para>a date of definition (optional)</para></listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
						    <term><code>description</code></term>
						    <listitem><para>an informative description (optional)</para></listitem>
						</varlistentry>
					</variablelist>	
					<para>
					The attributes of <code>anajava</code> are:
					</para>
					<variablelist>
						<varlistentry>
						    <term><code>name</code></term>
						    <listitem><para>A unique step identifier</para></listitem>
						</varlistentry>
					    <varlistentry>
						    <term><code>jar</code></term>
						    <listitem><para>The path to the jar</para></listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
						    <term><code>jad</code></term>
						    <listitem><para>The path to the optional jad</para></listitem>
						</varlistentry>					    
					</variablelist>
					<para>
					The attributes of <code>anadroid</code> are:
					</para>
					<variablelist>
						<varlistentry>
						    <term><code>name</code></term>
						    <listitem><para>A unique step identifier</para></listitem>
						</varlistentry>
					    <varlistentry>
						    <term><code>file</code></term>
						    <listitem><para>The path to the APK file</para></listitem>
						</varlistentry>
					</variablelist>					
					</section>
				</section>

	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>Standard analysis profiles</title>
		<section>
			<title>Android profile</title>
			<para></para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>MIDP profile</title>
			<para></para>
		
		</section>
    </chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>Developing analysis profiles.</title>
		<para>
		In this section, we present more technical things, that normal user should not modify.
		We explain how to understand analysis profiles and to write your own profile and present further
		configuration options.
		</para>
		<section>
			<title>Structure of profiles</title>
			<para>Profiles are standard jar files made mainly of resources and stored in <code>$MATOS_HOME/profiles</code>. They contain XML files
			    under the rule directory. They may also contain regular java classes declaring new custom checkers.
			</para>
			<para>
			    XML files can be split into several smaller chunks. This is a good practice as a complete profile can be several thousand lines long.
			    They are also usually split between basic analysis rules that are often extracted from an annotated version of the core Android or MIDP libraries
			    and presentation/scoring rules that are manually defined.
			</para>
			
			<para>A profile is organized in five steps:</para>
			<variablelist>
			    <varlistentry>
			        <term>header</term>
			        <listitem><para>General information on the profile</para></listitem>
			    </varlistentry>
			    <varlistentry>
			        <term>options</term>
			        <listitem><para>Customization of the tool (static analyzers) configuration</para></listitem>
			    </varlistentry>
			    <varlistentry>
			        <term>rules</term>
			        <listitem><para>Definition of the Java methods to be watched during the feature usage analysis phase.</para></listitem>
			    </varlistentry>
			    <varlistentry>
			        <term>reports</term>
			        <listitem><para>To associate messages to some result values of the feature analysis. It works mainly by pattern matching
			            against the result of the analysis. It is also at this level that a global structure to the final report is given
			        </para> </listitem>
			    </varlistentry>
			    <varlistentry>
			        <term>scoring</term>
			        <listitem><para>Scores are built by pattern matching against the final report. This is a crude but effective approach that gives
			            a lot of room for customization.
			        </para></listitem>
			    </varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
			<section>
				<title>Header and options</title>
				<para>A profile typically starts as shown below. The two first lines are
mandatory and must be written as shown. In the <code>&lt;matos&gt;</code>
tag, you're required to specify at least a name for the profile.
 Your entire profile data will be specified inside the
<code>&lt;matos&gt;</code> element.</para>
<programlisting>
  &lt;?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?&gt;
  &lt;!DOCTYPE matos SYSTEM "../matos.dtd"&gt;

  &lt;matos name="MyProfile"
         description="The purpose of the present profile is..."
         version="1.5"
         date="18.08.2006"&gt;
    
    ... your profile ...  
  
  &lt;/matos&gt; 
</programlisting>


<section>
	<title>General options</title>
	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<code>anasoot.enabled</code>
			</term>
			<listitem><para>
				activate the features usage analysis phase
				(boolean:
				<code>true</code>
				or
				<code>false</code>
				).
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<code>anasoot.enhancedPointsto</code>
			</term>
			<listitem><para>
				use an enhanced pointsto analysis
				that assign new objects to the results of method of the analysed
				profile. It
				creates more abstract objects and so gives more precise results (boolean:
				<code>true</code>
				or
				<code>false</code>
				).
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<code>anasoot.reportPseudo</code>
			</term>
			<listitem><para>
				activate the reporting of pseudo
				constants (boolean:
				<code>true</code>
				or
				<code>false</code>
				).
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<code>anasoot.loopAnalysis</code>
			</term>
			<listitem><para>
				performs an analyis of recursion for
				profiles that forbid the use of recursion (boolean:
				<code>true</code>
				or
				<code>false</code>
				).
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<code>anasoot.ruleDefaultFile</code>
			</term>
			<listitem><para>
				name of the default analysis profile
				(file name without the extension).
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<code>anasoot.treatConcatenation</code>
			</term>
			<listitem><para>
				enable treatment of appended
				strings (boolean).
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<code>anasoot.treatStringBuffer</code>
			</term>
			<listitem><para>
				enable treatment of basic operations on
				<code>StringBuffer</code>
				objects, a special kind of string in Java (boolean).
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<code>anasoot.treatValueOf</code>
			</term>
			<listitem><para>
				enable treatment of
				<code>String.valueOf</code>
				(boolean).
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<code>anasoot.treatStringOperation</code>
			</term>
			<listitem><para>
				enable treatment of basic
				operations on String objects (
				<code>trim</code>
				,
				<code>replace</code>
				, etc.) (boolean).
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<code>anasoot.treatFunctions</code>
			</term>
			<listitem><para>
				enable treatment of functions in
				general (followed by name and parameters) (boolean).
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<code>anasoot.treatSpyReturn</code>
			</term>
			<listitem><para>
				enable treatment of values returned by
				user's methods (boolean).
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<code>anasoot.treatSpyParameter</code>
			</term>
			<listitem><para>
				enable treatment of arguments passed
				to user's methods (boolean).
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<code>anasoot.treatSpyField</code>
			</term>
			<listitem><para>
				enable treatment of user's class
				attributes (boolean).
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<code>anasoot.printNodes</code>
			</term>
			<listitem><para>
				enable useless mentions of node numbers in
				report (boolean).
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<code>anasoot.rules</code>
			</term>
			<listitem><para>
				directory which contains analysis profiles.
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<code>anasoot.loopAnalysis</code>
			</term>
			<listitem><para>
				enable (default) or disable the analysis
				that points out recursive method
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<code>descriptorsChecking.enabled</code>
			</term>
			<listitem><para>
				enable the descriptors conformity check phase (boolean).
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<code>matos.cssFile</code>
			</term>
			<listitem><para>
				style sheet (CSS file) to use for the HTML
				reports (path to a CSS file).
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<code>matos.considerSameName</code>
			</term>
			<listitem><para>
				enable to recognize that a JAD file and a JAR
				file are relative to the same MIDlet suite if they have the same name,
				when you add all MIDlet suite of a directory (boolean).
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>
				<code>matos.xmlFormat</code>
			</term>
			<listitem><para>
				allow XML formatting of results (boolean).
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
</section>
	<section>
		<title>MIDP options</title>
		<variablelist>
		   <varlistentry>
			<term>
				<code>anasoot.midp-classpath</code>
			</term>
			<listitem><para>
				path to libraries which are used in the
				features usage analysis phase.
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>
					<code>anasoot.usedJSR</code>
				</term>
				<listitem><para>
					enable (default) or disable the analysis
					that points out the use of a set of MIDP JSR.
				</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>
					<code>anasoot.treatProperties</code>
				</term>
				<listitem><para>
					enable treatment of
					<code>getAppProperty</code>
					, with link to the JAD (boolean).
				</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>
					<code>descriptor.jad.endline</code>
				</term>
				<listitem><para>
					comma separated list of authorized
					characters to mark the end of line in the JAD file.
				</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>
					<code>descriptor.jar.endline</code>
				</term>
				<listitem><para>
					gives authorized characters to mark the
					end of line in the JAR manifest file.Typical values are
					<code>&amp;#x000D;</code>
					<code>&amp;#x000A</code>
					and
					<code>&amp;#x000D;&amp;#x000A</code>
					. You can specify several values by separating them with a comma.
				</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>
					<code>descriptor.mandatoryChapiId</code>
				</term>
				<listitem><para>
					boolean value (default false)
					specifying if JSR 211 content-handler must have an explicit ID
				</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>
					<code>descriptor.chapiContentTypesRegexp</code>
				</term>
				<listitem><para>
					optional regular expression
					defining constraints on the each content-type mentioned in a JSR 211
					handler
				</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>
					<code>descriptor.chapiActionsRegexp</code>
				</term>
				<listitem><para>
					optional regular expression
					defining constraints on the each action mentioned in a JSR 211 handler
				</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>
					<code>descriptor.chapiSuffixesRegexp</code>
				</term>
				<listitem><para>
					optional regular expression
					defining constraints on the each file suffix mentioned in a JSR 211 handler
				</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>
					<code>descriptor.midletSuiteNameRegexp</code>
				</term>
				<listitem><para>
					optional regular expression
					defining constraints on the name of the midlet suite
				</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>
					<code>descriptor.vendorNameRegexp</code>
				</term>
				<listitem><para>
					optional regular expression
					defining constraints on the name of the vendor of the midlet suite
				</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>
					<code>descriptor.jad.attributesorder</code>
				</term>
				<listitem><para>
					comma separated list defining
					the order of jad attributes (useful for some download portal that
					cannot handle attributes in random order)
				</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>
					<code>descriptor.jar.attributesorder</code>
				</term>
				<listitem><para>
					comma separated list defining
					the order of jar attributes (useful for some download portal that
					cannot handle attributes in random order)
				</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>
					<code>descriptor.jad.mandatory</code>
				</term>
				<listitem><para>
					additional list of attributes
					mandatory in the JAD. Use a comma separated list of attributes.
				</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>
					<code>descriptor.jad.forbidden</code>
				</term>
				<listitem><para>
					additional list of attributes
					forbidden in the JAD. Use a comma separated list of attributes.
				</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>
					<code>descriptor.jar.mandatory</code>
				</term>
				<listitem><para>
					additional list of attributes
					forbidden in the JAR manifest. Use a comma separated list of attributes.
				</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>
					<code>descriptor.jar.forbidden</code>
				</term>
				<listitem><para>
					additional list of attributes
					forbidden in the JAR manifest. Use a comma separated list of attributes.
				</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>
					<code>descriptor.midletSuiteIconSize</code>
				</term>
				<listitem><para>
					optional comma delimited list of
					authorized sizes for the midlet suite icons (as
					<parameter>width</parameter>x<parameter>height</parameter>
					)
				</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>
					<code>descriptor.maxMidlets</code>
				</term>
				<listitem><para>
					Optional constraint defining the maximum
					number of visible services (midlets) defined by the suite.
				</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>
					<code>descriptor.midletNameRegexp</code>
				</term>
				<listitem><para>
					optional regular expression
					defining constraints on the names of midlets (services) provided by the
					suite.
				</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>
					<code>descriptor.midletIconSize</code>
				</term>
				<listitem><para>
					optional comma delimited list of authorized sizes for midlet icons (as
					<parameter>width</parameter>x<parameter>height</parameter>)
				</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>
					<code>descriptor.pushURLRegexp</code>
				</term>
				<listitem><para>
					optional regular expression
					defining constraints on the URL defined for static push registry
				</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>
					<code>descriptor.pushRestrictionRegexp</code>
				</term>
				<listitem><para>
					optional regular expression
					defining constraints on the restrictions imposed for static push registry.
				</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</section>
				<section>
				    <title>Android options</title>
					<variablelist>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>
								<code>anasoot.android.global</code>
							</term>
							<listitem><para>
								makes a global analysis rather than a per component analysis of Android applications (boolean:
								<code>true</code> or <code>false</code>, the recommended default is	<code>true</code>).
							</para></listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry><term><code>anasoot.androidApiUse</code></term><listitem><para>
						    Enables the Api use analysis.
						</para></listitem></varlistentry>
					</variablelist>
				</section>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Static analysis rules</title>
			<para></para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Presentation of results</title>
			<para></para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Scoring system</title>
			<para></para>
		</section>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>Developping stub libraries</title>
		<para>
			Because it is hard to work on real implementation of runtime (they often
			depend on a lot of native code components) or
			sometimes due to licensing restriction (mainly for MIDP), and also for
			performance reasons,
			it is highly desirable to use simplified versions of the execution
			environment that only contain only a sketch of the
			actual data-flow/control-flow paths of those libraries. But doing so is a
			fastidious and very time-consuming
			task that we have tried to automate with the help of a stub generator
			application.
		</para>
		<section>
			<title>Stub generator basics</title>
			<para>
				The goal of the stub-generator is three fold:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Simplify the content of a library using introspection and
						annotations to understand what should
						be kept of the original code
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
				    <para>
					Generate low level analysis rules from annotations in the code
					because the actual code of the runtime is
					the best place to indicate which methods should be checked.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
				    <para>
					Generate a database of methods available in a given version of an
					environment. It is used to generate
					the list of available APIs in each version of Android.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Command line options</title>
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<code>-a &lt;filename&gt;</code>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>Adds an annotated jar file to the list of handled jars.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<code>-d &lt;folder&gt;</code>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para> path of the output folder.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<code>-db &lt;sqlite_database&gt;</code>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							path of the Sqlite database for API control to be used with the
							<code>-v</code>
							or the
							<code>-SDK</code>
							option.

						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<code>-jars &lt;classpath style list&gt;</code>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para> jars to handle.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<code>-r &lt;config.xml&gt;</code>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para> switch to the generation stub mode</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<code>-s &lt;config.xml&gt;</code>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>switch to the statistic mode</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<code>-v &lt;versionname&gt;</code>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para> record a new version of profile in the database.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<code>-w &lt;side file &gt;</code>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para></para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<code>-x &lt;outfile&gt; </code>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>XML mode with the result. Used to prepare analysis profile
							as they refer to the rules.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<code>-W</code>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>switch to witness mode.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<code>-SDK &lt;path to the SDK&gt;</code>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para> This is the normal way to generate a database for Android
							as it iterates on all versions
							on its own.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

			</variablelist>
		</section>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>Developping custom checkers</title>
		<para></para>
	</chapter>
</book>